Okay, בוקר טוב boker tov everybody.
Good morning, good morning. Today's דף daf is כח Chaf Ches 28.
No, is it? No. I'm sorry. I don't know where I am.
What's today's דף? daf? כז? Chaf Zayin? As I was saying, today's
דף daf is
כז. Chaf Zayin. Okay, seen a smaller דף. daf. Okay. And we
pick up at the bottom of כג עמוד ב, Chaf Gimmel Amud
Bais, 23b. שבועה שלא אוכל. sh'vuah shelo ochal.
So the גמרא Gemara says the following. So this is the person
takes an oath not to eat and it says that he eats
something not fit for eating and he's פטור. patur. And then it
moves on to talking about a person who takes an oath not
to
eat like takes an oath in general not to eat and he
eats dead carcasses or he eats חזיר chazir and it says he
transgresses. So the גמרא Gemara is going to initially think that there's
a contradiction because it initially thinks that what it means in the
beginning that if you eat something not fit for eating, it means
even if it's not halachically fit for eating. So now it's going
to have a problem because it because it reads the beginning of
the משנה Mishnah that if you make an oath not to eat
and you eat טרף treif food, you're פטור patur because that's not
halachically fit. And then the end of the משנה Mishnah says that
you're חייב. chayav. So what is the way to resolve this? So
we already know that רבא Rava says that the first part is
not talking about halachically unfit, it's talking about physically unfit, it's talking
about eating dirt and the like. Okay, but that's not initially what
the גמרא Gemara assumes or that or it doesn't assume that that
should make a difference. So let's take a look about fifteen lines
from the bottom on כג עמוד ב. Chaf Gimmel Amud Bais. הגופא
קשיא. Hagufa kashya. This is an internal contradiction. אמרת שבועה שלא אוכל
ואכל אוכלין שאין ראויין לאכילה ושתה משקין שאין ראויין לשתייה פטור. Amarta,
sh'vuah shelo ochal, v'achal ochalin she'ein reuyin la'achilah, u'shsam mashkin she'ein reuyin
lishsiyah, patur.
You said if somebody takes an oath not to eat and then
they eat food that's not fit for eating, not edible, and drink
that's not potable, that they are פטור. patur. And it assumes that
that would equally apply to dirt as it would to non-kosher food.
That all of that is not edible, either physically or halachically.
Okay. והדר תני, Vehadar tanni, and then the end of the משנה
Mishnah teaches, שבועה שלא אוכל ואכל נבילות וטריפות שקצים ורמשים חייב. sh'vuah
shelo ochal, v'achal nevelos u'treifos, sh'katzim u'remasim, chayav. That if somebody says
an oath they won't eat and they eat non-kosher food, חזיר, chazir,
dead carcasses, whatever it is,
McDonald's hamburgers, that they transgress. So it sounds like even if though
it's not fit for eating, again defining that halachically, thinking that that's
all the same, that you're חייב. chayav. So what's the story? Is
unfit חייב chayav or is unfit for eating פטור? patur? So the
גמרא Gemara says: מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? Mai sh'na reisha
u'mai sh'na seifa?
So what difference does it you know, מאי שנא רישא דפטור, mai
sh'na reisha depatur, why in the beginning are you exempt, ומאי שנא
סיפא דחייב, u'mai sh'na seifa dechayav, why in the end are you
חייב? chayav? So again, the easiest answer is that the beginning is
talking about something like eating dirt, which is not physically fit for
eating. The גמרא's Gemara going to get to that, but it's going
to have a very interesting discussion before it gets to that. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says: הא לא קשיא. Ha lo kashya. That's
not difficult. רישא בסתם סיפא במפורש. Reisha bistam, seifa bimfaresh.
When you just say in general, I won't eat, so won't eat
means then you're פטור patur for eating stuff that's not kosher because
that's not considered fit for being eaten. Again,
that's the רישא. reisha. Why in the end are you חייב chayav
if you eat טרף treif food? Because in the end, you didn't
just say you won't eat. You said, I won't eat טרף treif
food. You said it explicitly. Okay, now of course that's not in
the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, right. And well, it's not פשיטא pshita because
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish disagrees. Well, no, because ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
disagrees, he says even then אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur
chal al issur.
Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara explains it. If you just
say you won't eat, you're not liable for טרף treif food, that's
not considered fit for eating. But if you say you won't eat
טרף treif food, then you're being explicit, so you know, you can
be explicit and then you can reshape exactly what you mean. So
therefore in that case you would transgress. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says: במפורש נמי גופא תיתי תקשי? Bimfaresh nami gufa titchappai tikshay?
Even if you say the end is that you're explicit... Michael says:
and it's obvious, if you say you won't eat טרף, treif, then
you can't eat טרף. treif. But the גמרא Gemara says: No, even
if I accept that the end you said explicitly you won't eat
טרף, treif, it's not clear why you should transgress. Why? Because אמאי?
amai? מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא? Mushba ve'omed me'har Sinai hu?
He is already forsworn from הר סיני. Har Sinai. Okay, since you're
already, this is you know, bound by the תורה Torah not to
eat, your שבועה sh'vuah not to eat טרף treif food should not
be able to take effect on top of the תורה's Torah prohibition.
This is an idea that we've seen before, and we already know
the answer because this is like the fourth time maybe that we're
saying this. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: רב ושמואל ורבי יוחנן
דאמרי, Rav u'Shmuel v'Rabbi Yochanan de'amri, so רב, Rav, שמואל, Shmuel, and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan they all explain, here's how according to the
תנא קמא tanna kamma you get around the problem of מושבע ועומד
mushba ve'omed and you are the oath does take effect on טרף
treif food. בכולל דברים המותרים עם האסורים. Bekolel devarim hamutorim im ha'asurim.
That you say, I'm not going to eat kosher food and non-kosher
food. Okay, and therefore since your שבועה sh'vuah takes effect on the
kosher food, it also takes effect on the non-kosher. That's called an
איסור כולל. issur kolel. If the new prohibition has a larger scope,
it can double up, it can go on top of a pre-existing
prohibition. Okay, and we're going to get into that in a minute.
That's the case. Now I do want to just point out and
I have to admit I haven't seen all the תוספות Tosafos yet,
I'm a little behind, so... So maybe תוספות Tosafos discusses this, but
at least a glance he did not. This is a little problematic
because if you remember the last day or two, we've been saying
that when you say A and B, we treat it as two
separate שבועות. shvuos. Like שבועה shvua I won't eat apples and oranges,
and you eat apples and oranges, you get two sets of two
קרבנות, korbanos, because we treat that as two separate שבועות, shvuos, right?
As a שבועה shvua I won't eat apples and a שבועה shvua
I won't eat oranges. So if that's true, if a guy says
a שבועה shvua I won't eat kosher food and non-kosher food, then
it shouldn't be a כולל. kolel. It's not one big שבועה shvua
that because it takes partial effect on this, it takes effect on
that. It's two separate שבועות, shvuos, one about kosher, one about non-kosher.
The kosher should take effect, the non-kosher shouldn't take effect. So I
don't exactly get how it works. You know, maybe it would be
an example that would be a lot of food in front of
him on the table and he would say a שבועה shvua that
I won't eat any of the food here. So some of that
food is kosher and some is non-kosher, okay? But I just wanted
to put that out there given what we've been teaching until now.
You have to create a situation in which that's considered one שבועה
shvua and not two שבועות. shvuos. Alright, anyway, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara says. That's how it could take effect. You are explicitly
relating to non-kosher food, so therefore even though it's not edible הלכה-ly,
halacha you're specifically relating to it, okay? And
how does it take effect if it's already forbidden? So shouldn't we
say you can't take effect on top of an existing prohibition? No,
because this is a broader prohibition. You also are dealing with non-kosher
food. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר, amar, now ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says, אי אתה מוצא, ee ata motzei, no no no. If you
make a broader שבועה shvua that won't still take effect on top
of the טרפה treifa food, okay? אי אתה מוצא, ee ata motzei,
the only way you're going to get a שבועה shvua to take
effect on top of the טרפה treifa food is
אלא אי במפרש חצי שיעור ואליבא דרבנן, ela ee bimfareish chatzi shiur
v'aliba d'Rabbanan, that your שבועה shvua is forbidding you on something that
until now you're permitted. So either you say explicitly I won't even
eat a חצי שיעור chatzi shiur worth of this חזיר chazir or
of this McDonald's hamburger, okay? And because until now the תורה Torah
only prohibits you to eat a כזית, kzayis, obviously דרבנן-ly d'Rabbanan you
can't eat less, but the תורה Torah only prohibits you to eat
a כזית, kzayis, the fact that you said a חצי שיעור chatzi
shiur means that it took effect and it prohibited something that was
until now not prohibited. That would be one scenario according to the
רבנן Rabbanan that say you have to be explicit. אי בסתם אליבא
דרבי עקיבא דאמר אדם אוסר עצמו בכל שהוא, ee bistam aliba d'Rabbi
Akiva d'amar adam oser atzmo bechol shehu, or according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, it really would always work because when you take a
שבועה, shvua, it means even on a small amount, okay? So that's
why ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says איסור כולל issur kolel isn't going
to solve it. It has to take effect on top of something
that is right now permitted, and that something that's right now permitted
is less than a full כזית. kzayis. Now Charlie's hand is going
up because Charlie's going to remind us that according to that חצי
שיעור chatzi shiur is אסור מן התורה. asur min haTorah. But interestingly,
that's exactly a debate between ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, and it is ריש לקיש Reish Lakish who says חצי
שיעור chatzi shiur is not biblically forbidden. So ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish
answer makes a lot of sense according to his own position, okay?
Because he said it is not biblically forbidden and that's why the
שבועה shvua could take effect. And it is very tempting to think
that the reason רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan does not give ריש לקיש's
Reish Lakish answer is because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say that
a חצי שיעור chatzi shiur is biblically forbidden. So therefore it's not
like it's taking effect on top of something that's permissible, it's not
permissible. So תוספות Tosafos has a... but the גמרא Gemara never says
that. The גמרא Gemara never ties in the debate. Of course it
makes a lot of sense to tie it in. So therefore תוספות
Tosafos does a whole discussion right here דמוקי לה d'mokei lah anyway,
that תוספות Tosafos says maybe that's true. Maybe for רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, the reason he couldn't give ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish answer is
because for him a half a less than a כזית kzayis is
already biblically forbidden. Or he says maybe there's a difference between how
forbidden does it have to be biblically to say that a שבועה
shvua can't take effect on it? Let's say something is forbidden only
by a positive מצוה. mitzvah. Could a שבועה shvua take effect on
top of that? So תוספות Tosafos brings evidence from another גמרא Gemara
that yes. It doesn't have to be forbidden by a negative prohibition;
it's enough that it's just a positive. But תוספות Tosafos says it's
possible for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, even when he says a חצי
שיעור chatzi shiur is forbidden, it's even a weaker prohibition than a
positive מצוה. mitzvah. A positive מצוה mitzvah is at least explicitly in
the תורה. Torah. It's a thou shalt or thou shalt not. Okay?
When we say a חצי שיעור's chatzi shiur forbidden, it's learned from
like a inference from a subtle word in a פסוק. pasuk. So
that's more like the תורה Torah doesn't want you to do it
type of an idea, but it's not as explicit of a thou
shalt or thou shalt not. So תוספות Tosafos raises that question. How
forbidden does something have to be biblically to say a שבועה shvua
can't take effect on top of it? But he does acknowledge that
a very nice, elegant way of explaining why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
did not give ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish example of a חצי שיעור
chatzi shiur is because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan himself holds that a
חצי שיעור chatzi shiur is biblically forbidden. So maybe that's why a
שבועה shvua won't take effect. So let's take a look now at
what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara though doesn't say that.
So it says like this.
בשלמא, Bishlama, says the גמרא, Gemara, I understand רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
לא אמר כריש לקיש, lo amar k'Reish Lakish, he did not say
like ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, דמוקי לה למתניתין כדברי הכל. d'mokei lah
l'masnisin k'divrei hakol. He wants our משנה mishna to go like everyone.
He doesn't want to say it's either talking according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva that you weren't explicit, or according to the רבנן Rabbanan
that you were explicit. He doesn't want it to be getting into
the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Of course here's where תוספות Tosafos said the גמרא Gemara should have
said he didn't say like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish because he holds
that a חצי שיעור chatzi shiur is biblically forbidden, okay? But for
whatever reason the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. אלא ריש לקיש מאי
טעמא לא אמר כרבי יוחנן, Ela Reish Lakish mai ta'ama lo amar
k'Rabbi Yochanan, why does ריש לקיש Reish Lakish not say like רבי
יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Why does ריש לקיש Resh Lakish not say like
רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? Why didn't he give the example of an
איסור כולל, issur kollel, that if you made a bigger שבועה, shevuah,
bigger prohibition, it takes effect even on top of the thing that's
already forbidden? So אמר לך, amar lach, he'll tell to you, כי
אמרינן איסור כולל, ki amrinan issur kollel, yes, I generally agree there
is this principle of איסור כולל, issur kollel, right? The general problem
here is אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur.
If something is already forbidden, another state of forbidden status cannot take
effect on top of it. Now we've been saying, I just want
to alert you, we've been saying, how can your שבועה shevuah take
effect? Aren't you already מושבע ועומד? mushba v'omed? So this general question
which is, is the problem of אין שבועה חלה על שבועה, ein
shevuah chala al shevuah, and you're מושבע ועומד, mushba v'omed, it doesn't
have to be מושבע ועומד מהר סיני. mushba v'omed me'Har Sinai. One
is like, okay, there's already טרף treif and we all took a
שבועה shevuah on הר סיני. Har Sinai. The other is, I could
say, שבועה shevuah that I wouldn't eat this apple, and then again,
שבועה shevuah that I won't eat this apple, and forget הר סיני,
Har Sinai, and the second שבועה shevuah doesn't take effect because it
can't take effect on top of the first שבועה. shevuah. That's מושבע
ועומד. mushba v'omed. So there's a general question: is the idea that
a שבועה shevuah doesn't take effect on top of a שבועה shevuah
connected to part of, just a subset of the general principle of
אין איסור חל על איסור? ein issur chal al issur? One prohibition
does not take effect on top of another, right? That's the general
principle which we're going to get into right now. Okay, or is
this some separate problem of a שבועה shevuah on top of a
שבועה? shevuah? For now, we're going to assume that it is just
part of the generic issue that one שבועה shevuah can't, one איסור
issur can't take effect on top of another. And that's why we
say, oh, so if it's an איסור כולל, issur kollel, if it's
a bigger prohibition, then it can take effect on top, right? Because
they're basically, see, we're just going to enter into the general discussion
having nothing to do with שבועה, shevuah, that in general, שבועה shevuah
isn't special, one איסור issur can't take effect on top of another.
And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, okay, but when the second one
is bigger, it can take effect. So why does
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish not agree
with this? Because ריש לקיש Resh Lakish will
say, אמר לך, amar lach, כי אמרינן איסור כולל, ki amrinan issur
kollel, when do we say a bigger one takes effect? That's in
general, the general world of אין איסור חל על איסור, ein issur
chal al issur, באיסור הבא מאליו. b'issur haba me'elav. And the second
איסור issur comes by itself. You're not dealing with a שבועה. shevuah.
It's just the תורה Torah imposes it. Then if the second one
is bigger, it takes effect. Okay. באיסור על ידי עצמו לא אמרינן.
b'issur al yedei atzmo lo amrinan. But if the second thing is
a שבועה, shevuah, it won't take effect. So what is the example
of this, of something that comes by itself? Well, let's deal with
the case of non-kosher food. Okay, here I have my McDonald's hamburger.
Now I enter in, it's totally טרף, treif, okay. I enter into
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. The יום כיפור Yom Kippur is a bigger
prohibition. It makes all food, even kosher food, forbidden. The same way
a שבועה shevuah of all food makes kosher food forbidden, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur makes all food forbidden. So because יום כיפור Yom Kippur
made even my apples forbidden, it also makes this טרף treif hamburger
forbidden. And now if I eat this טרף treif hamburger, not only
do I violate, you know, eating a McDonald's hamburger, whatever, נבילה neveilah
and בשר בחלב basar b'chalav or whatever, I also violate, you know,
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's when the second one is bigger and
therefore takes effect also on top of this one, even though it's
already forbidden. Now ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says that's fine, that's when
the second one happens by itself. But if I take this McDonald's
hamburger and I say a שבועה shevuah that I won't eat it,
okay, because that is self-imposed, I'm creating that second איסור. issur. I
mean, I say a שבועה shevuah I won't eat any food. Because
it's self-imposed and I'm creating it, it cannot take effect even though
it's larger. Now why should self-imposed matter?
Who cares? So he's saying nothing to do with it being מושבע
ועומד? mushba v'omed?
Well, well maybe it does, we'll talk about that. Here's my McDonald's
hamburger, okay? I'm going to take a second and draw a nice
little bun. Okay, I don't know if that looks...
what's with the lettuce and the tomato?
Oh, okay fine. Okay fine, I don't know if that looks... it
looks like a little bit.
Maybe you're going to draw some חלה? challah? You get בשר בחלב?
basar b'chalav? And here are my apples. Here are my apples, okay?
So this is already, so this is already טרף, treif, okay. טרף,
Treif, okay. And then if what comes along is this thing called
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And that makes the
apples forbidden, then it's also going to make that thing forbidden. Okay,
that's a bigger thing. It makes this forbidden, it makes that...
everybody would agree to that.
It makes it forbidden a second time. Okay, but if what this
thing here is called a שבועה, shevuah, שבועה shevuah I won't eat
any food today or whatever, I won't eat. So he says just
because it makes the apples forbidden, says ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, it
doesn't make the טרף treif hamburger forbidden. Why? Because you created that
one, it didn't happen by itself. Now why should that matter? Who
cares? It should be the same mechanism. Who cares that you created
it? Okay, so I think that I'll give you two answers. One
answer is I think what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish could be saying
is what I said before, that the principle of אין שבועה חלה
על שבועה ein shevuah chala al shevuah is a different principle than
אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. From an
אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al issur thing, it
should work. But it's not just an איסור issur issue. It's an
idea that as a... A שבועה, shevua, a שבועה shevua only works
on top of something that is not that doesn't already is not
already bound by a שבועה. shevua. And that's not just the generic
problem of איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. And because
it's a שבועה, shevua, it has its own rules, and just because
it takes effect on the apple doesn't take effect on the hamburger.
That's one way of saying it. Okay, so he you know, that
he's basically saying שבועה shevua is a special problem called אין שבועה
חל על שבועה.
ein
shevua chal al shevua.
Why you would say then שבועה שלא אוכל ושבועה שלא אוכלנה shevua
shelo ochal veshevua shelo ochalena only be חייב chayav once? Everybody says
that. Right.
But the reason... Yeah,
exactly. But you could have just said it's a generic problem of
אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. So that's
the point. That he might be saying this is not just a
generic problem of אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al
issur. The other way of explaining ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, at least
what תוספות Tosafot says and sort of the גמרא Gemara gets into
a little bit, is he's not just saying you created it. Okay,
because you can create other things. Let's say you were מקדיש makdish
everything. You made it הקדש, hekdesh, right? You also created that, but
that actually would make the טריף treif hamburger, you know, אסור assur
in a second at a second level. So תוספות Tosafot says it's
not just that you created it, it's that you created it and
it only applies to yourself. It's a very subjective prohibition. Okay, and
now already you understand something. If you've got this objective prohibition called
יום כיפור Yom Kippur or even הקדש, hekdesh, it's something that applies
that you know, or something like that that creates an objective reality
as far as the whole world is concerned. So then you could
say it applies to this, it also applies to that. But something
that's very much it's my personal issue that I'm not going to
eat this type of a thing, so that's like weaker. And just
because it has the ability to relate to something כשר, kosher, it's
not seen as much of again I'm not really fully explaining it,
but I'm just saying because it's subjective, it doesn't have the same
weight. And just because it takes effect on one thing doesn't mean
it has the power to take effect on top of something else
that already has an objective איסור issur status. To add to that
objective איסור issur status your personal subjective you know שבועה, shevua, it's
not going to be strong enough if the thing is already forbidden.
So when do we say something that's already forbidden can become forbidden
again? When that happens by itself and it happens and it's an
objective type of a prohibition. But when you're creating it, you're it's
both you're the one creating it and it only applies to you,
it's not strong enough to take effect on top of something that's
already you know prohibited.
So it wouldn't make a difference then if he did a נדר
neder and then a שבועה shevua on top of it? Presumably, right.
It's already אסור assur to you. Yes, yes. What's the purpose of
this double prohibition on?
Oh, so then if you for example eat this טריף treif hamburger,
like do you have to bring do you not only get lashes,
but you don't get a קרבן korban for a hamburger, but you
get a קרבן korban for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? So you
have to bring a קרבן, korban, right? If you did it intentionally
would you get two sets of lashes? You know, those types of
questions. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בשלמא לריש לקיש,
Bishlama le-Resh Lakish,
I understand according to ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, משום הכי קפטר רבי
שמעון. mishum hachi ka patar Rabbi Shimon. Now I understand why רבי
שמעון... Rabbi Shimon... So the רבנן Rabbanan say it works because we're
dealing with חצי שיעור. chatzi shiur. Remember, he's now explaining the משנה,
mishnah, that the משנה mishnah was a case of חצי שיעור. chatzi
shiur. You said even a half of a כזית kezayit and that's
why it can take effect on top of the טריף treif hamburger.
So he says now I get why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees
and says it doesn't take effect. Why? דתניא, De-tanya, it works out
beautifully. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon goes according to his reasoning. רבי שמעון
אומר כל שהוא למכות ולא אמרו כזית אלא לקרבן. Rabbi Shimon omer
kol shehu lemakot velo amru kezayit ella lekorban.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that actually the even a less than
a כזית kezayit is forbidden and you would get lashes for it.
There's no minimum amount for lashes. You might remember that going back
to מכות. Makkot. So now it's perfect. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says
the reason the רבנן Rabbanan say you get lashes, the reason the
שבועה shevua took effect, was because you were referring to less than
a full amount, less than a כזית, kezayit, and that's where it
took effect. Therefore, that was something that was until now permitted. While
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says the שבועה shevua doesn't take effect because
he says that was never permitted. I would even have given the
guy lashes for less than a כזית. kezayit. So that's why the
שבועה shevua doesn't take effect. It very elegantly explains the משנה. mishnah.
אלא לרבי יוחנן, Ella le-Rabbi Yochanan, but according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan
that says the reason the רבנן Rabbanan say it takes effect was
because it was a bigger שבועה, shevua, it was a bigger scope,
and because it took effect on one thing it took effect on
the other, and that's why the רבנן Rabbanan say it works because
of
איסור כולל, issur kolel, מאי טעמיה דרבי שמעון דפטר? mai ta'ameih de-Rabbi
Shimon depatar? Why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagree with that? The
גמרא Gemara says one minute. מידי
הוא טעמא אלא משום איסור כולל? Midi hu ta'ama ella mishum issur
kolel? One minute, you just said that the only reason you're חייב
chayav is because of this principle of איסור כולל. issur kolel. רבי
שמעון לטעמיה דלית ליה איסור כולל. Rabbi Shimon le-ta'ameih de-leit lei issur
kolel. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon rejects completely what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
said, איסור כולל issur kolel doesn't apply to שבועה. shevua. Like ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish rejected it by שבועה shevua and therefore he needed
a different reason, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees for even a bigger
reason. He doesn't hold of איסור כולל issur kolel at all. Okay,
what's the example? דתניא, De-tanya, רבי שמעון אומר האוכל נבילה ביום הכיפורים
פטור. Rabbi Shimon omer ha-ochel neveila be-Yom HaKippurim patur. And look, it's
exactly our case of the example I gave. Okay, I wonder why
I gave that example. Somebody who eats a נבילה neveila on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, פטור, patur, you're exempt from a קרבן korban of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. You didn't violate יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. It's
crazy. If you eat a McDonald's hamburger on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you violated
eating... Anyway, because once it was אסור assur because it was נבלה,
neveila, it didn't have a כשר kasher שחיטה, shechita, it can't be
אסור assur from another perspective as well.
You're עובר over on נבלה, neveila, not on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon rejects the idea of איסור כולל issur
kollel and that's why it works out very elegantly. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says the reason you're חייב chayav here and it's not already
prohibited is because it's a lesson for כזית. kazayit. And רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon says you're פטור pattur because it was already אסור assur
less than a כזית kazayit because he says less than a כזית
kazayit you get lashes. According to רבי יוחנן, Rebbe Yochanan, the reason
it's אסור assur even though it was already forbidden was because it
was an איסור כולל, issur kollel, right? And you made a broader
שבועה shvua where רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says you're פטור, pattur, I
don't believe once something is אסור assur it can't be אסור assur
a second time. It works out very elegantly. Yes.
So Rabbi Simon would not participate in some of these discussions we
get in the גמרא Gemara about how many איסורים issurim can you
violate at once?
Correct. Correct. All those fun questions of I can do one thing
and get six transgressions or whatever, for רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon it
would not apply. Yes.
And so מן התורה min haTorah if you eat בשוגג b'shogeg something
that's a נבלה neveila what's- what are you supposed to do? Bring
a קרבן? korban?
Do תשובה. teshuva.
And you're supposed to bring an עולה olah or something or?
No, you're not technically חייב. chayav. You do תשובה. teshuva. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now... what for יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur? Michael's asking first for- for the McDonald's hamburger what do you
do if it was בשוגג? b'shogeg?
טרייף treif food on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you would just...
Oh oh...
Not according to רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. According to רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon you would not even though יום כיפור Yom Kippur is weightier
and even though it's an איסור כולל, issur kollel, רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon says that it does not- that does not make it forbidden.
It was already forbidden. Okay so now but we don't rule like
רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. Or we generally assume we don't rule like
רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. Okay, anyway. בשלמא לריש לקיש משכחת לה בלאו
והן. Bishlama l'Reish Lakish mishkachat lah b'lav v'hein. Now the גמרא Gemara
introduces a new requirement for a שבועה shvua that you are not
aware of yet. Okay remember a שבועה shvua is learned out certainly
the קרבן, korban, right? And our general context here is if you
violate the שבועה shvua you bring a קרבן. korban. So at least
the פסוק pasuk by the קרבן korban says, right? What does it
say? It says להרע או להיטיב, l'hareia o l'heitiv, right?
That you made a שבועה shvua to do bad or to do
good. Which basically means the גמרא Gemara interprets לאו והן lav v'hein
that the שבועה shvua would either be to do something or to
not do something. And therefore says the גמרא Gemara one of the
requirements for a שבועה shvua to be binding is that you could
have had to have been able to take the שבועה shvua in
the reverse. Okay? So if you say, I don't know, let's take
this case, a שבועה shvua that I won't eat a נבלה. neveila.
So then well that you could not... I'm sorry. Well yeah, I
won't eat a נבלה, neveila, correct, thank you. I won't eat a
נבלה. neveila. You cannot be חייב chayav because you can't say the
reverse isn't possible. A שבועה shvua that I will eat a נבלה
neveila is the opposite of an איסור חל על איסור. issur chal
al issur. It's a שבועה לבטל את המצווה. shvua l'vatel et hamitzva.
Okay, a שבועה shvua that is to bind you to do a
transgression is not a binding שבועה. shvua. So therefore the גמרא Gemara
says so wait a minute we got a problem here. How does
it work that you take a שבועה shvua to not eat this
McDonald's hamburger? How could it take effect? It's not the לאו והן.
lav v'hein. You can say you won't do it but a שבועה
shvua to say you would do it wouldn't be binding. So it
says well for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish we've got an answer because
at least putting the rabbinic issues aside you could take a שבועה
shvua to eat a half a כזית kazayit of a McDonald's hamburger.
That would not- I mean obviously it would be a disgusting thing
whatever but it would not be biblically prohibited by the תורה. Torah.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא לריש לקיש
משכחת לה בלאו והן. Bishlama l'Reish Lakish mishkachat lah b'lav v'hein. I
get that you could- I mean again it's a little unpleasant or
whatever, inappropriate, but you could in theory take a שבועה shvua to
eat a half of a כזית kazayit because that is not biblically
forbidden so you can take a שבועה shvua to not eat half
of a כזית. kazayit. אלא לרבי יוחנן Ela l'Rebbe Yochanan in בשלמא
לאו משכחת לה. bishlama lav mishkachat lah. Of course so good you
could take a שבועה shvua not to eat this hamburger because you're
saying a broader שבועה. shvua. I'm not going to eat anything right?
I'm not going to eat טרייף treif food. I'm not going to
eat כשר kasher food. Okay so therefore you've got that. Okay yes
you can do it. It's a bigger שבועה. shvua.
But אלא הן היכי משכחת לה? ela hein heichi mishkachat lah? Where
do you get the הן? hein? Because again remember the גמרא Gemara
said before now that you were מפרש, mefaresh, you were explicit. You
said I'm not going to eat טרייף treif food and I'm not
going to eat כשר kasher food. Well because you were explicit you
can't reverse this because to reverse it you would have to say
a שבועה shvua I will eat טרייף treif food and I will
eat כשר kasher food. Well you can't take a שבועה shvua that
you'll eat טרייף treif food. Right does everybody get it? Okay so
because the גמרא Gemara said the case was that you're explicit it
says it won't work for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish because you can't
say the reverse.
So the question is how much of a reverse? You say I'll
eat all food you mean?
Well no you'd have to say the reverse of the way you
formulated it. Exactly. Yes so the only reason the גמרא Gemara is
in this bind is because we said it was מפרש. mefaresh. If
we hadn't said מפרש mefaresh then you could have said if I
say a שבועה shvua that you won't eat food it automatically includes
טרייף treif and then you could reverse
it a
שבועה. shvua.
כדרבא. k'd'Rava. You're right. You know what? Forget our point that said
that you were explicit. That's what got us into this whole problem
initially. And we had to say you were explicit because we thought
if you just said סתם stam you won't eat, that you're exempt
by eating טרף traif food. That that's considered inedible. The גמרא Gemara
says we were wrong. טרף traif food is not considered inedible. When
the משנה Mishna says you're not liable for eating something inedible, you
would transgress if you ate a McDonald's hamburger if you סתם stam
say שבועה shevua you won't eat. So what is it that you
don't transgress for? So the גמרא Gemara says דאמר רבא שבועה שלא
אוכל ואכל עפר פטור. d'amar Rava shevua shelo ochel v'achal afar patur.
If you eat dirt. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going
back. And the גמרא Gemara is saying look, if you say שבועה
shevua I won't eat, the משנה Mishna says if you eat something
inedible you're exempt. That does not include טרף traif food. If you
ate טרף traif food, you would violate. What that means is if
you eat something that's physically inedible, you eat dirt, that's the case.
Okay? That you're exempt. So now when it says if a guy
says a שבועה shevua that I will eat, that I won't eat
and eats טרף traif food he transgresses, you don't have to say
that he explicitly labeled טרף traif food. A person just says שבועה
shevua I won't eat anything today and eats טרף traif food, he
transgresses. That's not considered inedible. That's totally edible with a prohibition, but
it's not inedible. Okay? And therefore now it works. So why when
a person says a שבועה shevua I won't eat טרף traif food
does it take effect... I won't eat any food today, does it
take effect on top of the טרף traif food? Because of the
איסור כולל, issur koleil, right? But now the שבועה shevua is not
just I won't eat טרף traif and kosher, he doesn't have to
be מפרש. mefareish. We thought before he had to be מפרש, mefareish,
right? But now we realize he doesn't have to be מפרש. mefareish.
He just says...
if he can't, let's say he said it that way, I won't
eat, let's say he actually said it that way, I won't eat
טרף traif food.
Well then it wouldn't work because then it would not be reversible.
Okay, but if he just says שבועה shevua I won't eat today,
okay, then you don't have to be מפרש. mefareish. It takes effect
on טרף traif food. This is not considered inedible, this is totally
considered edible and it takes effect on טרף traif food. And the
reason it takes effect is because since it is generic, specifically because
it's not מפרש mefareish and because it's one big broad שבועה, shevua,
since it takes effect on the apple, it takes effect on the
hamburger. And therefore it is also בלאו והן, belav v'hen, 'cause the
reverse of this שבועה shevua is I will eat today. So the
שבועה shevua I won't eat today works 'cause the reverse also works:
I will eat.
If he said I will eat today and
eats טרף traif food...
then
he fulfilled his שבועה. shevua. Correct. Okay, so that's how it works.
It works 'cause of כולל, koleil, it is reversible, and as long
as... but and you do not say specifically I won't eat טרף
traif food, okay? You don't have to say that and it wouldn't
work to say that. This does apply, this is considered edible, the
only thing that's not edible is dirt, yes.
What is this requirement about the having...?
This is the first time we're introducing it. The גמרא Gemara is
going to be more מפרש mefareish about it later. The גמרא Gemara
knows what the גמרא Gemara is going to say in the next
rest of the פרק. perek. Okay, but here we're now just sort
of taking it for granted that you understand that's a requirement.
So where did it originate?
From the פסוק pasuk that says להרע או להיטיב. l'hareia o l'heitiv.
That if you make a שבועה shevua to do bad or to
do good, which means that a שבועה shevua has to be reversible.
You have to be able to
say it one way or the other.
I understand, but that's not how the גמרא Gemara reads it, yeah.
When we say it wouldn't work, it would only just not work
on the טרף traif part, but would work on the kosher part?
If I say a שבועה shevua I won't eat kosher food and
I won't eat טרף traif food...
well that depends if we look at it as two
שבועות shevuot or as one.
Well, what are we saying right now?
Well that's an interesting question. If we look at it as one
and part of it is reversible, does that part take effect? I
don't know the answer offhand. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רב מרי אף אנן
נמי תנינא. Amar Rav Mari af anan nami tanina. You know what?
It's also clear in... we also taught this in the משנה, Mishna,
that non-kosher food is considered edible. Our initial assumption was wrong that
we thought non-kosher food was inedible unless you're מפרש. mefareish. Even if
you're not מפרש, mefareish, even if you're סתם stam generic, non-kosher food
is considered in the edible category. Okay? Because what's the case? The
end of the משנה. Mishna. קונם שינני נהנית לי, Konam she-enani nehenit
li, if a man says my wife will be forbidden to be
as קונם konam as a קרבן, korban, forbidden in benefit to me,
I can't get benefit from her, אם אכלתי היום, im achalti hayom,
if I ate anything today. ואכל נבלות וטרפות שקצים ורמשים, v'achal nevelot
u'traifot shekatzim u'remasim, and he actually had gone to a McDonald's earlier
today, okay, הרי אשתו אסורה לו, harei ishto asurah lo, his wife
is forbidden. So you see, says the גמרא, Gemara, that clear in
our משנה Mishna that eating includes
eating non-kosher food. Okay? You don't have to be מפרש. mefareish. The
only thing eating doesn't include is if he ate dirt, then
he would not have fulfilled his...
then
his קונם konam would not take effect. But non-kosher is considered eating.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכי השתא, hachi hashta, wait, that's not
a good comparison. התם כיון דמעיקרא אכל, hatam keivan d'mei-ikara achal, since
in the morning he went to the McDonald's. And then
והדר אשתבע *v'hadar ishtaba*, and then it took the שבועה shvua, *shvua*
effect, technically not a שבועה shvua, *shvua*, it's a נדר neder *neder*
in this case, stop by אחשביה *achshavei*. He's already given weight to
the McDonald's hamburger. He already ate it. Okay, there's a general principle
called like אחשביה *achshavei*. There's a whole question on like יום כיפור
Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, if you take certain medication, does the act
of or the most, better, but that's a little advanced, but the
act of swallowing it makes it into food or on פסח *Pesach*,
stuff that's inedible, does the fact that you actually ate something inedible
make it like food? The fact that you did it?
I swallowed dirt, it doesn't make it into food.
I understand, so there's stuff sometimes in a middle category. It wouldn't
work by dirt, but maybe it works by טרף *treif* food. If
you consider maybe טרף *treif* food in general is considered inedible, but
it's not as inedible as dirt, so maybe when you eat it
you have shown that at least as far as you're concerned it's
edible and that raises its status. So therefore, גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
the order might
matter. If the guy went to the McDonald's already, he has already
through his actions made it clear that this hamburger is edible. Okay,
we wouldn't say the same by dirt but we would say that
by a טרף *treif* hamburger. And then when he says, like, my
wife is forbidden if I ate something, well through his actions he's
already defined that he's done an act of eating, he's eaten something
edible. Okay, but that's very different than if the order is reversed.
If somebody says a שבועה shvua *shvua* that I won't eat, then
at that moment he has yet to eat a טרף *treif* hamburger,
so we would say that maybe he there that's not including טרף
*treif* food. טרף *treif* food for him is considered inedible and maybe
that's outside of the שבועה shvua. *shvua*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara's*
statement that the question do you consider טרף *treif* food to be
edible or inedible when a person says a שבועה shvua? *shvua* that
I will eat, a שבועה shvua *shvua* I won't eat, a נדר
*neder* that I haven't eaten, says it might depend on the order.
If the eating has, if the טרף *treif* food hasn't been eaten
yet, it's considered inedible. It's actually interesting from a perspective also of
like taboo. You know, some things we consider to be like unthinkable,
completely off-limits, right, and so on, you know, and then once they're
done, now they're thinkable, now they're you know, and now they're so
anyway, so before he's ever eaten טרף *treif* food, what's that's inedible,
that's a חזיר *chazir*, nobody would eat that, whatever, of course, no
that's I don't mean that by eating, that's completely you know, you
know, inedible, but after if a person's already eaten it and then
he's taking a שבועה shvua *shvua*, now he's considering it to be
edible. So it's very interesting psychology of the גמרא gemara, *Gemara*. So
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says you can't prove from the end of
the משנה Mishna, *mishna* whether טרף *treif* food is considered to be
edible if you have yet to eat it. But nevertheless, that's our
statement, that if a person takes a שבועה shvua, *shvua* not to
eat, then included in that eating is טרף *treif* food. טרף *treif*
food is considered edible even though it's forbidden. The only thing that
would be excluded and you don't have to be explicit, טרף *treif*
food is included and it's an איסור כולל issur kolel *issur kolel*
and that's why it takes effect. The only thing that's excluded is
something that's really inedible like dirt. אלא הכא מי אחשביה *ella hacha
mi achshavei*. In our case, before it's done you don't have אחשביה
*achshavei* so you can't prove it from there, but nevertheless that is
what we are saying. אמר רבא amar Rava: מאי טעמא דמאן דאית
ליה איסור כולל mai taama deman de-isa issur kolel *Amar Rava: Mai
ta'ama d'man d'is lei issur kolel*? What is the reason that איסור
כולל issur kolel, *issur kolel* works? Why just because it takes effect
on the apple does it take effect on the hamburger? Good, now
we're going to get into the mechanism of איסור כולל issur kolel,
*issur kolel*. So he says, מידי דהוה אאיסור מוסיף midei de-hava a-issur
mosif, *midi de'hava a'issur
mosif*. It works just like איסור מוסיף issur mosif *issur mosif*. Well,
that explains it. Okay, so ומאן דפטר u-man de-pater, *u'man d'patar*, I'll
just read and then explain, דלית ליה de-leisa leh, כי אמר איסור
מוסיף issur mosif. בחדא חתיכה בשתי חתיכות chatichos לא אמרינן *d'lais lei,
ki amar issur mosif b'chada chaticha,
b'shtei chatichos lo amrinan*. Okay, he doesn't hold of this. He would
say איסור מוסיף issur mosif *issur mosif* works on one piece, it
doesn't this is talking about two pieces. What's this one piece, two
pieces, etc.? So here's the, I'm going to give an example. So
the best example here of this, I am sorry because it talks
about piece and objectifies women and a person, but it's a very
I think like relatable example. Here you've got this woman, okay. Now,
she is this man's, no, sister, okay.
So she is forbidden to that man, okay. Or she is this
is ראובן Reuven's *Reuven*, we're going to get, no, and we're going
to get to her being another man's wife in a minute, לאה
Leah, *Leah*. לאה Leah *Leah* now marries מרדכי *Mordechai*. That's number one,
she starts by being a sister. Now she gets married to מרדכי
*Mordechai*. Okay,
married.
Okay, that happens later in life.
I hope so. Well, you know, he could be a very late
sibling. If ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* were to, God forbid, have sex with
his sister, would he also transgress the prohibition of sex with a
married woman? And that is a case of not איסור כולל issur
kolel, *issur kolel* but איסור מוסיף issur mosif *issur mosif*. When מרדכי
*Mordechai* here married לאה Leah *Leah*, okay.
But that did, what it did not say more things are forbidden
to a person, right this says, this starts being forbidden to me,
this new prohibition makes more things forbidden to me. It makes the
apple, so it'll make this double forbidden to me. That's what an
איסור כולל issur kolel is. It expands the number of things that
are forbidden. Okay, so
this is important, what is the difference between כולל kolel and מוסיף.
mosif. כולל kolel is expands
the number of things
that are forbidden. Not only is the hamburger forbidden to me, now
that it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur. or a שבועה, shvua, an apple's
forbidden to me as well. Okay, when he got married to לאה,
Leah it wasn't like from ראובן Reuven. perspective, oh, now more women
are forbidden to me. That had nothing to do with more women
that are forbidden to me. What happened, לאה now, who only was
forbidden to one person, because of her marriage is now forbidden to
the whole world. Okay, you got that? Those arrows mean forbidden. I
should have drawn them in red. Okay, red means forbidden. So she
goes from being forbidden to one person to being forbidden to the
whole
world. Okay, so an איסור מוסיף issur mosif is, it doesn't expand
the number of things forbidden, it expands
the number of prohibitions,
or no, the number of people
who
are to whom the prohibition relates,
or the number of people to whom the object is forbidden, again,
I apologize for
the
object. This woman is now not just forbidden to one person, she's
forbidden to the whole world. Okay. Now, if you had to pick
which one of these makes more sense that something could become doubly
forbidden, okay, which one makes more sense? That this thing becomes doubly
forbidden because an apple also became forbidden? Or that this woman becomes
doubly forbidden because she now became forbidden to more people? Which would
you say?
You have a sense which one of those makes more sense to
say that because of this new thing, this thing now becomes doubly
forbidden?
Because there's more people.
Right, because this thing affects לאה herself. It says לאה now
is not just forbidden to ראובן, she's forbidden to the whole world.
Her status is changing, right? Her status vis-a-vis everybody in the world,
now she's an אשת איש, eshes ish, she's a married woman. So
her status has become married woman to the whole world, so you
know what, it also becomes married woman to ראובן. This thing changes
the thing's status itself, and what Rava is saying is that it
also changes it vis-a-vis the person to whom it was already forbidden.
So this actually makes sense, an איסור מוסיף. issur mosif Once she's
going to become a forbidden world to the rest, a married woman
to the rest of the world, she'll be a married woman to
you also, she'll have שני לאוין.
shenei lavin. Exactly. Whereas this case, okay, just because an apple is
forbidden, it's not making it obviously clear why a cheeseburger should be
forbidden. So what, the apple's forbidden? Why should that mean the cheeseburger
is forbidden? This was already forbidden.
The initial mechanism did not affect the status of the cheeseburger. Okay,
so that's what רבא Rava says. So let's read that. So remember
this because איסור מוסיף issur mosif. and איסור כולל issur kolel everybody
gets wrong, and this is the basic difference, okay, expanding the number
of things or taking the one thing and expanding it to whom
it's forbidden, and this makes it clear why איסור מוסיף issur mosif?
is more obvious because this already changes the status of the person
or the object it or him or herself. What? Remember it for
the final, it will definitely be on the final. Okay, so
אמר רבא: Rava מאי טעמא דמאן דאית ליה איסור כולל issur kolel
מידי דהוה אאיסור מוסיף, mosif. yeah same thing, if איסור מוסיף issur
mosif makes it forbidden a second time, איסור כולל, issur kolel?
so I would agree to that, right?
איסור issur מוסיף mosif? everyone agrees to. ומאן דפטר, now רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who exempts איסור כולל, issur kolel דלית ליה, he doesn't
hold that, כי אמר איסור מוסיף בחד חתיכה, ki amar issur mosif
be-chad chaticha,
when one piece thing is forbidden and now it's forbidden a second
time, that second status to other people, that second status affects even
the first person.
בשתי חתיכות אמרינן, be-shtei chatichos amrinan, but just because an apple becomes
forbidden, it's not clear why the cheeseburger should become forbidden a second
time.
I think חתיכות can actually apply to pieces of meat somehow?
Yeah, well this would be a צבי. tzvi. If this could be
a kosher piece of meat, a צבי, tzvi, whatever.
No, the other one, in איסור issur מוסיף. mosif.
Yes, you can have that not just with people. Okay, we're going
to get an example where it's also by objects. Yes, it's just
this is just a very obvious clear example. Okay. Okay. Okay, וזה
אמר רבא veze amar Rava and רבא Rava says למאן דאית ליה
איסור כולל, leman de'is lei issur kolel, according to the one who
holds of איסור כולל, issur kolel. אמר שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים amar
shvua shelo ochel teenim וחזר ואמר שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים וענבים, vechazar
ve'amar shvua shelo ochel teenim ve'anavim,
if a guy first takes an oath that he won't eat figs
and then he says I won't eat figs and and grapes, מגו
דחייל אענבים חייל נמי אתאנים, migo dechayal a'anavim chayal nami a'teenim, because
it takes effect on the on the grapes, it takes effect on
the figs. Like this is a duh, this is what we have
been saying all along. פשיטא? pshita? Obviously. No, מהו דתימא, mah d'teima,
I might have thought איסור הבא מאליו אמרינן, issur haba mei'elav amrinan,
איסור הבא מעצמו לא אמרינן, issur haba me'atzmo lo amrinan, exactly what
why רש לקיש Resh Lakish rejected this. Maybe איסור כולל issur kolel
only works when the second prohibition comes automatically. When you impose the
second prohibition, maybe it doesn't take effect. So maybe by שבועה, shvua
you're not able to say איסור כולל issur kolel because you've created
it. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we do say. Okay, which is
exactly the debate of רש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. Do we say that if the שבועה shvuah is bigger, it
takes effect, or do we say, no, the mechanism doesn't work there
because you created the second שבועה. shvuah So now we've set up
before as the debate of רש לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, now we're going to actually discuss that issue itself. Does
איסור כולל issur kolel. work in the context of שבועה? shvua. I
need to repeat the points though that I really don't understand it.
If a guy says a שבועה shvua, I won't eat dates and
figs or whatever, figs and whatever he said, figs and grapes, why
isn't that two separate שבועות? shvuot? We've been saying from until now
that it's two separate שבועות, shvuot, two separate קרבנות. korbanot. So why
is it one big שבועה shvua, that that takes effect that works
like איסור כולל? issur kolel, I just don't get the... I mean,
I see how you could frame it in a way that it
would be one שבועה, shvua? but the way the example the גמרא
Gemara is giving does not work well with the earlier discussion. Anyway,
now we're going to go ahead and see whether this idea, does
איסור כולל Issur Kollel work by a שבועה, shvua or does it
not work because a שבועה shvua is self-created. Yes.
So to me it could be different like the same thing can
be different to different people. In other words, like let's say I'm
just trying to think about the דחיות. dechiyot. So if I say
I took a נדר on it, you know, and then I made
it הקדש, hekdesh, right? So then can that be איסור issur מוסיף?
mosif. Yeah, totally. Yep. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתיב רבא בריה דרבא,
metiv Rava brei deRava, רבא Rava the son of רבא Rava, asked.
I don't know, that's a different רבא, Rava I guess. Anyway, יש
אוכל אכילה אחת וחייב עליה
ארבע חטאות ואשם אחד. yesh ochel achila achas vechayav aleha arba chatat
ve'asham echad. So here we're going to get an example of one
piece of meat. As Tommy was saying, Rav Shimon told of these
because these a lot of these are איסור issur כולל. kolel, One
piece of meat that has five prohibitions wrapped up in it. You're
only way it's going to... and therefore one bite is going to
give you four sin offerings, four חטאות chataot and one אשם. asham.
Okay. And the only way that it can have all those prohibitions
in one bite is if you hold of איסור issur מוסיף mosif.
and איסור issur כולל kolel, that allows other prohibitions to stack up.
Okay. What's the example?
And now we're going to sort of show I'll show how this
idea how these will work out. ואלו הן, ve'eilu hein, these are
they: טמא שאכל חלב, tamei she'achal chelev, an impure person, a טמא
tamei person ate forbidden fat, והוא נותר, vehu notar, and this was
forbidden fat that was
leftover, you know, that was brought as a קרבן. korban. It was
the fat of an animal that was a קרבן korban and it
wasn't burned on the altar the day that it was brought. So
it has the status of נותר, notar, leftover, you
know, meat or fat of a sacrifice. והוא נותר מן המוקדשים, vehu
notar min hamukdashim, from stuff that's been sanctified, and he ate it
ביום הכפורים, beYom HaKippurim, on Yom Kippur. Okay. So he got the
trifecta or the quint-secta or whatever that is. Okay. So now
let's talk about how this works. How did how did one thing
stack upon another? Okay. So this thing, you start with the חלב.
chelev. When the animal is born, okay, here's a little baby animal,
okay, I'm making it small. Okay, it's got in it some some
חלב. chelev.
It's got in it some fat. All the fat inside of it
on the day that it's born, that's איסור issur number one. Starts
with an איסור of חלב. chelev. Okay.
Now, you comes along and you are מקדיש makdish it. Okay. You're
מקדיש makdish it. That's what you do, number two. Okay. Does that
take effect on the חלב chelev of the animal? Well, yes, because
to the rest of the animal... because although the חלב chelev was
forbidden already to everybody, but now it's כולל, kolel right? The הקדש
hekdesh takes effect on the meat part of the animal, so that
is כולל, kolel. okay, כולל kolel. because it it expands
objects. What are the objects it expands? The meat. Okay, that's איסור
number two.
Oh, but it also expands the number of people too? No, for
the
חלב... chelev... meaning right. Meaning like now the animal's forbidden to everyone
because because you know, meaning it expands the objects.
Not only is this חלב chelev forbidden, other objects are forbidden. It
doesn't expand the scope of the איסור of חלב. chelev.
No, not on חלב. chelev.
So it's כולל. kolel It's כולל. kolel? It's not מוסיף. Mosif This
is a good test to see. This is going to be the
final test question, okay? This will determine, do you understand the difference
between כולל kolel. and מוסיף? Is this כולל? kolel. well it refers
to the meat, it does not expand the scope of חלב. chelev.
No, not of חלב, chelev, man. Okay, one minute Johnny. Okay, then,
okay, you go ahead and you bring it as a, so that's
מוקדשים. mukdashim. Then you bring it as a קרבן korban and you
leave it over to the next day.
I see because making a קרבן korban makes it
an additional prohibition on top of נותר notar because the...
No, that is, number two is מקדיש, makdish, so you made it
a קרבן. korban. Then you left it over to the next day.
Now, what did that do? This whole thing was already forbidden to
the whole world, so what did נותר notar do? What נותר... notar...
you הקדשתה hikdashta it if it was a קרבן, korban, you can
eat part of it, can't you? Next thing you know, with נותר
notar no one can eat any part of it. That's what it
does.
Yeah, but the... but that’s the meat. What did you do to
the חלב? chelev?
Okay, נותר notar is related to חלב, chelev, is that what you
mean?
It’s all about the חלב. chelev. The חלב chelev is the focus.
Okay, so now the חלב chelev has two prohibitions at this stage.
Now you left the stuff over.
Well, now it can't be on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Ah, so what it does, the נותר notar does, is it takes
this חלב, chelev, that’s the חלב, chelev, and it says not only
is the חלב chelev אסור assur to a person but it’s אסור
assur למקדש. lemikdash. I don’t know why that’s a person, I was
supposed to draw a mouth. It expands the איסורים, issurim, it’s now
also can’t be brought as a קרבן. korban. Okay, so this חלב
chelev is now אסור, assur, the scope is now אסור assur to
two, for an extra purpose. It’s the scope of the חלב chelev
itself has expanded. So that is an
איסור of what
type? מוסיף. Okay, that is מוסיף. That now has taken the same
object and say there are more things it’s forbidden to, not more
people in this case but more ways in which it’s forbidden. It
has changed the status of the object itself. Okay, that’s מוסיף. Then
you became טמא. tamei. Now, now what? You are טמא. tamei. Okay,
that doesn’t change the status of חלב. chelev. The חלב chelev was
forbidden to you until now, okay? It doesn’t make the חלב chelev
forbidden to more people. But what it does is, as far as
you’re concerned, now not only is חלב chelev forbidden to you, other
things are forbidden to you as well. Okay, all the whole world
of קרבנות korbanot are now forbidden to you because you’re טמא. tamei.
So that is an איסור of כולל. kolel Oh good, you’re getting
it, okay? Because now the object hasn’t expanded its scope, more objects
are now included in the things that are forbidden to you. So
because your טומאה tumah status made קרבנות korbanot forbidden to you, it
made the חלב chelev forbidden to you another time, okay?
Meaning because now you can’t burn it, right? Like what would you
do with it? You were supposed to burn it.
No, you... there’s nothing new you can’t do with the חלב. chelev.
Okay, that’s the point of כולל. kolel. כולל kolel, doesn’t change the
status of the חלב, chelev, it changes the other things you can’t
do. It just adds another layer of prohibition, it’s not qualitatively different,
that’s the point. Okay, so number five is now becomes יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur Well what יום כיפור Yom Kippur does is, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur? means not only are you forbidden in the world of
קרבנות korbanot which you were now, now you’re forbidden in all food.
I see, so that’s another כולל.
Kollel That’s another כולל, okay?
Like you said before with the cheeseburger.
Right, exactly. Okay? So now this is no more forbidden than it
was before but now more things are forbidden to you so that
adds another layer of forbiddenness on that. Okay, so that was a
great test question, alright? So therefore, okay, so we have that. Now
these are, are these things, all of these are חטאות chataot with
the exception of הקדש hekdesh which is מעילה, me'ilah, that’s an אשם.
asham. So that’s why it said four חטאות chataot and one אשם.
asham. Alright, so let’s take a look.
Okay, fine. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, אפילו היתה שבת הוציאו
חייב. afilu hayita Shabbat hotzio chayav. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says hey,
I’ll get you a sixth one. You were eating this חלב chelev
as you were walking on שבת Shabbat and you were doing הוצאה
hotza'ah while you were eating it.
On שבת Shabbat and יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? Yeah. Well because... why didn’t he say that for יום
כיפור? Yom Kippur. So רש"י Rashi says he assumes that there’s no
איסור of carrying on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur אמרו לו, amru lo,
אינו מן השם. eino min hashem. Give me a break, that’s not
part of eating, that’s just completely incidental, fine.
But when they get the death penalty wouldn’t it be any...?
Well, no, it’s all בשוגג. beshogeg. Anyways, ואם איתא ve'im ita says
the גמרא, Gemara now according to you רבא Rava that you think
that and also ר' יוחנן Rav Yochanan that you can have איסור
כולל by a שבועה shvua. even though it’s self-imposed,
I can get a sixth prohibition here. Make a שבועה shvua, on
it, okay? ואם איתא ve'im ita says the גמרא Gemara and if
what you’re saying is correct, blah blah blah, where am I?
משכחת לה חמש. mishkachat la chamesh. I can have five חטאות chataot
and one אשם. asham. כגון דאמר שבועה שלא אוכל תמרים וחלב. kegon
de'amar shvuah shelo ochal temarim vechelev.
Okay, and before יום כיפור Yom Kippur because then יום כיפור Yom
Kippur makes it even bigger, even makes other כשר kosher food. Okay,
and מיגו דחייל אתמרים, migu dechayal atmarim, if it takes effect on
the... you know on the figs... חייל נמי אחלב, chayal nami achelev,
it takes effect on the חלב. chelev. So he says,
כי תני איסור במילא, ki tani issur bame'ela, איסור במילא. issur bame'ela.
Now, our this discussion here is not talking about self-imposed שבועה. shvua.
The הלכה halacha is correct, even though it's self-imposed, it would take
effect, okay, and it would say איסור כולל.
You mean just for שבועה, shvua right? Just for שבועה, Shvua because
הקדש hekdesh is not בא מאליו. ba me'elav.
Right, so the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that. The
גמרא Gemara is going to get to that, okay. But it just
so happens we're talking about things that are imposed by the תורה.
Torah. We didn't, we decided not for the purposes of this discussion
to also include things that you could create yourself, okay. But אין
הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, the הלכה halacha would be correct. So
the גמרא Gemara says, as Michael, Michael's too smart for us again,
the גמרא Gemara says, והרי הקדש. ve'harei hekdesh. What do you mean
we're not talking about things that you generate? You generated הקדש, hekdesh,
you sanctified it. It says בבכור דקדושתו מרחם. bi'bechor dikdushato me'rechem. No,
we're talking about an, you didn't sanctify it, it was a בכור.
bechor. And since it was a בכור, bechor, therefore it, the,
everything here came automatically, not because of any act that you did,
okay.
Wait, so that means that הקדש hekdesh part isn't really true?
So it's not clear. Is the גמרא Gemara here saying that, no,
presumably it is true הקדש, hekdesh, but we just don't happen to
be talking about it, okay. And that's the way he gets out
of it. Why didn't he give שבועה? Shvua We don't want to
talk right now about things that you create yourself. אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami, the הלכה halacha would be the same, but we're
just not talking about it, okay. איבעית אימא, iba'is eima, or if
you want to say the following. כי תניא, ki tanya, here's another
reason we didn't mention it. Not that the הלכה halacha is true,
but it wasn't the scope of our discussion. כי תניא מידי דלית
ליה שאילה, שבועה דאית ליה שאילה לא תניא. ki tanya midi de'leis
lei she'eila, shvua de'is lei she'eila lo tanya. We're not talking about
about prohibitions that you could in theory undo. A שבועה Shvua you
could undo, you could go to a חכם, chacham, do a התרת
נדרים hataras nedarim or התרת שבועה. hataras shvuos. שאילה she'eila means you
could ask, you know, sort of go through that process and undo
it. So אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, the הלכה halacha would
be true if you didn't undo it you would bring another קרבן
korban because of it. But you, but we're not talking about those
types of איסורים. issurim. So the גמרא Gemara says again, והרי הקדש,
ve'harei hekdesh, okay, how about הקדש? hekdesh? אוקימנא בבכור. ukimna bi'bechor. Okay,
same thing we said before, we're not talking about, we're talking about
הקדש hekdesh that came automatically. So the point
is שבועות shvuos just isn't in the scope of our discussion, okay.
It's true the הלכה halacha is correct.
Wait, can you undo הקדש? hekdesh? Yeah.
Okay, but we are not talking about things that either you have
created or things that could be undone, okay. And the case of
הקדש hekdesh is בכור, bechor, so it's just not part of our
scope of our discussion. איבעית אימא, iba'is eima, or if you want,
here's another explanation, which is the best. So basically you're saying אין
הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, the
הלכה halacha is true, don't ask me about this, we just weren't
talking about it. And here's a much simpler explanation why we weren't
talking about it. כי תניא קרבן קבוע. ki tanya korban kavua. Because
by a שבועה Shvua you bring a קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh
ve'yored and we wanted to talk about how many fixed-value קרבנות korbanos
you could bring. So all of the חטאות chataos here are fixed-value
קרבנות, korbanos, so we didn't want to talk about a שבועה. Shvua,
And an אשם, asham, well אשם's asham also fixed-value. קרבן עולה ויורד
לא תניא, korban oleh ve'yored lo tanya, we didn't want to be
talking about those types of קרבנות. korbanos. That to me is like
the best answer.
But I thought we were talking about the number of קרבנות korbanos
you bring, not necessarily the number of fixed קרבנות. korbanos.
Well, that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. The scope of our discussion, we're
talking about fixed קרבנות. korbanos. The גמרא Gemara says, one minute, והרי
טמא שאכל את הקדש דקרבן עולה ויורד הוא. ve'harei tamei she'achal es
ha'hekdesh de'korban oleh ve'yored hu. One minute, the קרבן korban of מעילה
me'ilah of a טמא שאכל את הקדש tamei she'achal es ha'hekdesh is
actually is a variable cost price קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara
says, בנשיא רבי אליעזר היא דאמר נשיא מייתי שעיר. bi'nasi rebbi eliezer
hi de'amar nasi meisi sa'ir. No, it's a special case that if
it's a נשיא. nasi. If it was one person? If it's a
king, exactly, right, then in his case, I don't want to get
into the details, he would say for this type of a קרבן
korban it actually is a fixed קרבן, korban, so I don't want
to get into the specifics, but anyway that's an answer, okay. רבי
אשי אמר לא, כי תניא מידי דחייל כשיעור, שבועה דחייל אפחות מכשיעור
לא תניא.
Rebbi Ashi amar lo, ki tanya midi de'chayil
ki'shiur, shvua de'chayil apachos mi'kishiur lo tanya. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says,
here's another reason that it wasn't part of the scope of the
discussion. Yes, the הלכה halacha is true, but we wanted to talk
about things that had a minimum amount associated with them. A שבועה,
Shvua you could structure it that it doesn't have a minimum amount
associated with it.
Meaning because of משהו? mashu?
Because you could say משהו, mashu, and we didn't want to confuse
the discussion, so even if you didn't structure it that way, we
didn't want to talk about those types of things. But the גמרא
says wait a minute, והרי הקדש והרי הקדש, ve'harei hekdesh ve'harei hekdesh,
הקדש hekdesh doesn't need a כזית. kezayis. Okay, אבל בעינן שוה פרוטה.
aval ba'inan shaveh prutah. There still is a שיעור shiur to it,
a פרוטה's prutah worth. So we just didn't want to be talking
about prohibitions that could have effect even with less than a minimum
amount. ורב אשי מאוירא אמר רב זירא, כי תניא זדונו כרת, זדונו
לאו לא תניא. ve'rav ashi me'avira amar rav zeira, ki tanya zedono
kares, zedono lav lo tanya. We're only talking about things that the,
that if you did it willfully you get כרת. kares. All these
things you get כרת. kares. We didn't want to talk about שבועה.
Shvua אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, שבועה Shvua you bring a
קרבן, korban, it would take effect איסור כולל, but it's only a
regular regular prohibition, so we didn't want to include those. The גמרא
says wait a minute, והרי אשם דזדונו לאו וקתני. ve'harei asham de'zedono
lav ve'katani. But back to the מעילה, me'ilah, that's not כרת, kares,
believe it or not, מעילה me'ilah according to, some say it's מיתה
בידי שמים, misa bi'yedei shamayim, but according to one major opinion, it's
just a simple negative prohibition. So you can't say we're not talking,
we're only talking about כרת kares worthy prohibitions. The גמרא says, בחטאות
קאמינא. be'chataos ka'amina. No, within the types of
חטאות. chataos. But within the חטאות Chatta'os that we're talking about, we're
talking about a traditional חטאת Chattas that has a כרת Kares behind
it. We're not going to be talking about a שבועה Shvua, that
is a חטאת, Chattas, you bring a sin offering but it's a
sin offering without a כרת Kares behind it. It's similar to the
answer of we're not talking about variable חטאות. Chatta'os. We're talking about
a standard חטאת. Chattas. So yes, אשם Asham is not a חטאת,
Chattas, but within the world of חטאות, Chatta'os, we only want to
talk about standard ones, fixed value ones that have a כרת Kares
behind it. So would it be true if you took a שבועה
Shvua here, would you also have to bring a קרבן, Korban, would
it take effect? Yes, but it's just not the topic of our
discussion. Okay, let's just finish the משנה, give me one more minute.
רבינא אמר כי קתני מידי דחיילא אמידי דבר אכילה הוא. Ravina Amar
Ki Kasni Midi DeChaila A'Midi DeVar Achila Hu. We're talking about the
types of prohibitions that apply to food objects. שבועה דחיילא אמידי דלאו
בר אכילה, Shvua DeChaila A'Midi DeLav Bar Achila, but a שבועה Shvua
that can take effect even on non-food objects, you could take a
שבועה Shvua, about dirt, לא קתני, Lo Kasni, that's just not the
scope of our discussion. Again, אי הכי נמי, Ei Hachi Nami, הלכה
Halacha is correct, not the scope of our discussion. הגמרא Gemara says
one minute, פריי, Frei, הקדש דחייל נמי אעצים ואבנים. Hekdesh DeChail Nami
A'Etzim V'Avanim. What do you mean? I can sanctify wood. Okay, so
were we talking about a בכורה? Bechorah?
No, but the nature of the prohibition. Okay, if you were, if
you made a שבועה, you didn't have to be talking about non-food
objects, but the nature of a שבועה can take effect on non-food.
So the גמרא says, but we are talking about those types of
things. הקדש Hekdesh can take effect on non-food objects. אלא
כי קתני, Ela Ki Kasni, fine, forget that answer. מידי דחיילא אמידי
דאית ביה מששא. Midi DeChaila A'Midi DeIs Bei Mashasha. We're talking about
types of prohibitions that take effect on physical things. שבועה דחיילא אמידי
דלית ביה מששא, Shvua DeChaila A'Midi DeLeis Bei Mashasha, but a שבועה
can take effect even on a non-physical
thing, כגון שישן ושלא יישן. Kegon She'Ishan V'SheLo Ishan. Someone takes an
oath that I'll take a nap today, I won't take a nap
today. That's not a physical, that's not object, physical object related. And
that's a good general distinction. All of these things are object related.
What, יום כיפור maybe is more person related? But anyway, but a
שבועה is action related. So we're not talking, say, we're talking about
types of prohibitions that more relate to physical objects directly, לא קתני.
Lo Kasni. So basically, a whole series of answers why we weren't
talking about שבועה, but אי הכי נמי, Ei Hachi Nami, שבועה would,
even though שבועה is self-generated according to רבא and רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and whatever, everybody other than ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, because שבועה,
even though it's self-generated, if you make it with a larger scope
we would say איסור כולל and it would take another layer of
effect. But now you have learned the difference between כולל and מוסיף
and I don't want you to get that wrong and it's going
to be on the final.